In this episode of the podcast, I have an
amazing guest, who has come a long way from
reporting unexploitable bugs to Google, which
were denied, through valid bugs and being
on their hall of fame, up until working at
Google and improving browser security mechanisms.
The name of my guest is Michał Bendkowski.
Enjoy.
Hello, Michał.
Thank you so much for joining me in today's
podcast.
To start off, can you tell me and our audience,
what is your background and how did you get
to the point you are currently at?
Start wherever you want to start.
Hey, everyone.
Hey, Greg.
So, I started my career in cybersecurity around
10 years ago.
I was a contestant for many, many years, and
that was like my main job.
I was always interested more in attacking
than prevention.
In 2014, I think, or 2013, I started Bug Bounty
as a kind of a side job.
I was hacking mainly Google programs, like
Google Web VRP and the Chromium.
Well, I also imported some bugs in some other
Bug Bounty platforms.
After many, many years working as an attacker,
at some point, I decided that instead of finding
an XSS number 100, maybe it will make more
sense in trying to do some stuff that will
prevent this XSS from happening in the future.
Or maybe if we cannot prevent that, then maybe
we can do something that will mitigate the
side effects of this vulnerability.
So, in essence, I was on the offensive side
both in my daily job and in bug hunting.
But recently, I started my shift from the
offensive to the defense.
And where do you work now?
So, now I work at Google.
I joined Google at the beginning of this year.
I am in the information security engineering
team.
We actually recently started a blog on bughunters.google.com,
which is like the blog specifically of our
team, which I think is pretty nice.
And this team does many different things.
But in essence, what I'm interested in is
trying to prevent as many bug classes as possible.
And the perfect way to prevent a bug class
would be if that would be possible in the
web platform.
So, a developer of an application doesn't
have to do anything, but we make some changes
in the specifications or in the implementations
of browsers.
And thanks to that, everybody is safer, basically.
Yeah, that's very annoying to us attackers
when browsers make changes, because then it
applies to pretty much every single application
at once.
Whereas, when it's some changes in the server-side
frameworks, like, I don't know, introducing
prepared statements for SQL, it takes years,
long years before everyone uses the new change.
But in browsers, it's pretty much instantly
after it gets to the stable branch of Chromium
or whatever, it's just everywhere.
So, that's something I don't like.
Yeah, I think from my perspective, that's
pretty cool.
Even if the application is not supported at
all, but people update their browsers and
the auto-updating mechanisms in browsers are
pretty good, then they can still profit from
the changes that we make.
And yeah, in a nutshell, my job now is that
the more I will annoy you, the better.
Yeah, unfortunately, that's true.
What back class are you working on at the
moment?
I'm trying to prevent mutation XSS.
That's one of it.
Basically, there is a change that I made in
Chromium a few months ago to change how HTML
is serialized, maybe how DOM tree is serialized
to the HTML.
Because the mutation XSS, like the root cause
of mutation XSS, is that if you have a DOM
tree and then you serialize it and then you
parse it again, then you are not guaranteed
that the first DOM tree will be equivalent
to the second DOM tree.
I think, by the way, that it is a really bad
feature of HTML, because imagine that if you
had a JSON, if you had an object, and you
would serialize an object to JSON, and then
you would deserialize this JSON to an object,
and you would get a completely different object,
then you would say that it is pretty bad.
But this is exactly what happens in the HTML,
and it is actually by design.
There is an actual warning in the HTML specification
that when you do a run strip of HTML and a
DOM tree, you are not guaranteed to get the
same stuff that you got before.
There are basically two main surfaces on which
we need to work with.
The first one is deserialization of attributes,
because there was a decision made in the HTML
working group, and that was like 10, 15 years
ago, I think, that characters such as the
less than character and the greater than character
are not escaped in attributes.
This is actually bad, because it might happen
that something that was supposed to be an
attribute will be mistreated as an open stack.
It is actually a really slight change that
they are trying to make, is that when you
serialize an attribute, then the less than
character is serialized to ampersand lt and
the greater than to ampersand gt.
But what's also interesting and something
that I need to work with right now is that
we added a use counter to Chromium.
So use counter is basically when we try to
make a change that we believe can be backwards
incompatible, then we are adding counters
to Chromium, and we want to see how many people
actually use a feature, so how likely it is
to break the web.
And it turns out that, if I remember correctly,
around 5% of page loads serialize attributes
with less than or greater than characters
in them, which is much greater than I had
expected before.
It doesn't mean that if we make the change,
like to say with Chromium, the sites will
break, but there is a potential that they
might break.
So we are doing some kind of analysis to see
if this will really happen.
And another problem, besides attributes, is
that some tags, such as style, this is the
most prominent example, when you serialize
the style, then you don't do any escaping.
So inside style, the less than character is
just serialized as the less than character
without the entity.
And this also can be abused in mutation access.
There is basically no way in the HTML spec
to safely serialize a style tag, because if
it contains the nstack for, I mean, if you
use the DOM API and you set like style.textContent
is equal to nstack to style and then some
stuff after that, then there is no way to
serialize that safely.
And yeah, I'm also trying to do something
about that.
But this is actually super, super tricky.
And I am not even sure if that's possible
at this moment.
You know, I mean, it is possible, but can
we do that without breaking the web?
That's the question.
But when it comes to the attributes, it's
also tricky because of the highest percentage
of usage.
So yeah, we need to do some more analysis
before we can say that it is safe to flip
this flag in the stable chromium.
By the way, if you use the chromium flag called
enable experimental web platform features,
then the serialization algorithm is changed
to the attribute.
So if you use that flag and if you see that
anything breaks, please report it back to
chromium or let me know, because I would be
very interested in any use case that it actually
breaks.
I use that flag on a daily basis for a few
months now, and I don't think I saw anything
breaking, but that's just like anecdotal.
One person.
That's not enough.
I think it can also, if I understand this
correctly, it can also break some CSP bypasses
where you could only inject an attribute and
then you used, I think, bootstrap with data
HTML attribute and the value of the attribute
became an actual HTML.
So if I understand correctly, this will also
break the CSP bypass.
I mean, if you use a DOM API like get attribute
or like a data set and you get the value of
an attribute, that it doesn't change.
Like the parsing doesn't change.
Okay.
Only the serialization.
So I don't think that this bypasses will.
Okay.
So serialization here means using what exactly?
That you have a DOM tree and you create a
textual output from the DOM tree.
Okay.
So you create an HTML text from the DOM tree.
Because maybe let me explain why is this a
problem, because I think I didn't explain
that.
The problem is like if you have an HTML sanitizer
and well, HTML sanitizers usually work this
way, that you have an input string that you
consider able and it outputs another string
that is supposed to be safe.
But what happens internally is that the HTML
sanitizer parses the HTML, it traverses the
DOM tree and it removes everything that it
considers bad.
And then it needs to serialize to a textual
output to a string.
But then when you do something like if that
inner HTML is equal to like DOM purify sanitize
something, then the HTML is parsed again.
Okay.
Because the sanitizer serialized the DOM tree.
But when you assign something to inner HTML,
then it is parsed again.
And that's the problem because you might set
a DOM tree that the sanitizer considers safe,
but it is not safe after another reparsing.
That's basically a mutation exercise.
So the problem is that, for instance, one
example of a mutation exercise that actually
happened in Google a few years ago.
There's a video by Live Overflow about it.
It was done by Masato Kinagawa.
Basically, you have a no script element in
the HTML specification.
And it is a very interesting element because
it is parsed differently depending on whether
you have scripting enabled or disabled.
So if your scripting is enabled, then no script
is treated pretty much as style.
I mean, it is parsed pretty much the same
way.
So everything inside is treated as text.
But if you have scripting disabled, then it
is parsed as this, basically.
So two completely different parsing modes.
And the problem is that if you use the browser
provided HTML parser, such as DOM parser,
parse from string, then it parses the HTML
as if the scripting was disabled.
By default, is it disabled or enabled?
Disabled.
And you can change that.
It is assumed that the scripting flag is disabled,
and it is always parsed this way.
There is no way in the API to change that.
But when you assign to innerHTML, then you
obviously assign it to a document which has
the scripting enabled.
So the problem is that the sanitizer parses
the no script kind of differently than how
it will be parsed afterwards.
So suddenly, you might have a DOM tree that
the sanitizer considers safe.
And after that reparsing, and the difference
in no script, it is no longer safe.
There are other examples where after a few
parsing trips, you can have very different
effects.
But I think this is the easiest one to explain
why this is a problem, why this might occur.
And by the way, if you use a sanitizer that
exposes, like client-side sanitizer, that
exposes an API that it can return not a string,
but a DOM node, then use it, because then
you don't have any problem with mutation access,
because the HTML is not reparsed.
Yeah, yeah.
These things, I got a little bit into like
knowing the more advanced or hidden, I don't
know, you can say features of HTML, like namespaces
and types of nodes and everything you say
like here.
So guys, if you are new to this, I recommend
you blog posts by Michal.
They are really good.
And I'm not only saying this because you are
my guest.
I actually did mostly use your write-ups to
learn about this stuff, which actually did
lead to the XSS, let's say, in Golang's HTML
library, which didn't use, which wasn't as
advanced as those things, but I'm happy that
I've learned something.
But I know that you didn't start your bug
hunting career or your web security career
by finding these, let's say, state-of-the-art
XSSs.
I think you started with the very simple ones.
So can you tell me what was the first bug
you ever reported?
I mean, when it comes to my bug hunting career,
the first bug I reported was an XSS in Google
Blogger, and it was actually discarded.
I mean, I didn't get any work for that because
the attack scenario was that I needed to send
a zip file to the victim and the victim needed
to upload it themselves.
So, yeah, I mean, I think I agree that, like,
if I can make a victim do that, then I would
just put something else in the zip file that,
you know, take over their computer.
Why bother with that XSS in that case?
Yeah, so that was the first bug I reported
in Bug Bounty, but I think I reported some
bugs before, just, like, you know, casually
I found something in some library.
I think, like, my first part, like, the first
report that I did for some external software
was to PHPMyAdmin, and I think that was in
2011, maybe, something like that.
That was completely, you know, inexploitable
XSS, but there was a bug that I might, you
know, misremember the details, but it was
something like that, that if you use, like,
order by in your SQL query, then in the result,
the PHPMyAdmin would say that this is a result
from to, and if you put an SQL comment in
that, then it would just, you know, reflect
that SQL comment.
So, if you put, like, a snippet of HTML in
the comment, then it would just, you had an
XSS in that case, but it was inexploitable
because that was basically, that was like
a self-XSS, pretty much, because it has, like,
C-SERV token and all stuff like that, but
the other was a bug that just didn't escape
data as they should, or maybe they should
cast it to an integer.
I think that's what they ended up doing.
Yeah, but, you know, I was thinking if I should
report that or not, because I knew it wasn't
explainable, but then I, I mean, I found that
maybe they would say that, okay, it doesn't
matter.
I also didn't really brag about this report.
I don't think I ever put that even on my Twitter
or anything.
There is a CVE for that, which I think is
pretty funny, because, yeah, but, you know,
I think that, like, recently there's been
a discussion about the usefulness of CVEs,
and, like, somebody reported on SQL injection
in the vulnerable web application, so, yeah,
CVEs are pretty useless sometimes.
But, yeah, I got CVE from that, even though,
but, you know, I didn't brag about it, because
it wasn't anything special or anything exploitable.
Yeah, I think a lot of us just start with
bugs that are not exploitable, and then as
we go, we learn about the attack scenario
and how important this is, that it's something
practical.
Can you tell me how did you then transition,
let's say, from self-exercises into ones that
were rewarded?
Yeah, I mean, I think that my work as a pentester
was very, I mean, yeah, so the work as a pentester
gave me really much here, because I was talking
to clients constantly, and oftentimes we had
discussions whether a bug is exploitable and
whether we should consider this bug a security
issue, if it's, like, a high severity or medium
severity or stuff like that.
So, like, the discussions with customers made
me, you know, think more about the attack
scenarios.
And by the way, I actually am thinking about
hosting a video on my YouTube channel about
that, about the attack scenarios and when
an attack makes sense, when it doesn't make
sense.
But I think, like, during my pentesting career,
like in Securitum, I was a person who tended
to lower the severity of bugs, like the most
of all people, because, yeah, I remember,
I think I can, I won't share any specific
details, but, like, some general idea.
I remember that I was testing some application
in, like, a pentest of an application, and
I found a SQL injection, and at that point,
in my head, SQL injection was pretty much
an automatic, you know, high severity or critical
severity.
But, okay, I tried to exploit it further,
and this was a SQL injection in an insurance
application, and you could insure your car
in that.
So, it turns out that the database contained
only data about cars, so, you know, models,
manufacturers, types of engines, and stuff
like that.
There was absolutely no data of users.
And, you know, when I reported a bug, and,
like, automatically, I gave it, like, high
severity, but before sending this report,
I just, you know, stopped for a while, and
I was just thinking to myself, what if the
customer comes back and asks me, why is this
the high severity?
And then I realized that I can't convince
myself that this is high severity, because
I didn't, you know, gather anything from that.
I, everything that was in the database was
public data anyway.
So, yeah, I remember that was the first time
that I know the severity of SQL injection.
I don't remember if it was medium or too low.
What was that?
But it wasn't, like, high severity, because
it's just, you know, I couldn't, how can I
convince somebody else that it is high severity
if I cannot convince myself?
I think that was a pretty, pretty important
moment for me, because it made me realize
that you cannot just have an automatic assignment
that this type of vulnerability is this type
of severity.
You know, all depends on many different factors,
like how, what kind of data you can access,
how likely the attack, like, I don't know.
I guess that some people consider, like, start
XSS as more severe than reflected XSS, but
it also doesn't have to be true in all cases.
There might be cases where reflected XSS will
actually be more likely to execute than started
XSS.
Like, if there is, like, a super common application,
like Google Docs, for instance, and if you
have a reflected XSS in Google Docs, then,
you know, it's very, very easy to mount an
attack.
But if you have a started XSS in a web interface
of some network device that the admin visits
once a year, then, you know, XSS might never
actually get executed.
So, yeah, I think that during my pentesting
job, and, you know, clients keep talking about
that they just like to not agree with the,
you know, assignments of severity.
And when it happens over and over again, then
you start thinking about it more.
You kind of like to prepare and to think about
what they might say, what might be their arguments,
what they might not like about this vulnerability,
about this scenario.
Oftentimes, it's difficult to, you know, as
a pentester, you only see a fragment of the
whole ecosystem.
You might not understand how everything is
connected.
Because right now, I was talking that we might
consider a vulnerability a high severity,
but the client might consider it lower.
But sometimes, it was actually the other way
around.
Sometimes, we didn't consider something very
severe, but the client knew how it interacted
with some different parts of the system.
Or maybe that we didn't consider something
serious, but the client knew that doing some
stuff actually generates some costs.
And if you can do that, like without limits,
then it's a pretty serious problem for them.
Then, you know, it also can happen this way
around.
So, yeah, like over all of these years, I
really like whether an attack scenario is
viable, whether it makes sense.
And I always like to think about the preconditions
for an attack.
So, you know, the main question is, if we
consider an attack scenario, and we know that
the attacker has to be in a certain place
to mount this attack, are there other attacks
that are much, much simpler than that that
they can do, given this, you know, precondition?
It's like I said with the XSS in Blogger.
That was my first XSS report in Google Backbone.
Like, if we can make somebody take a zip file
from us and do something with that, then why
would we bother with an XSS in, you know,
a Blogger admin interface?
We would probably be able to match more severe
stuff without having to have any, you know,
vulnerability in the application itself.
You maybe could just make them run DevTools
and do something in that, or maybe just run
an executable from the zip file.
So, yeah, that's the change that happened.
But I think it just comes with experience.
You see how people react, what it imparts,
and then you understand also their point of
view.
That not every vulnerability that you find
is something that the world needs to stop
to fix that.
And there might actually be vulnerabilities
that people might acknowledge, but they might
decide that they don't want to fix that right
now or maybe for the next couple of months.
And it can also make sense when you keep the
threat model in mind.
Yeah, I think I started paying more attention
to the actual impact in the sort of bug bounty
world than in the pentesting world.
In pentesting, I feel like there was more
using of pre-written templates of bug descriptions
and things like that, because when you report,
you know, 10, 15, 20 vulnerabilities in one
week...
By the way, if I can interrupt, I actually
hated that.
I mean, I didn't use template descriptions.
I hated doing that.
Really?
Yeah.
Would you write a personal description of
every single bug in pentest?
I mean, yes.
For most of them, yes.
Like, only for...
Wow.
Like, if I have an exercise, then I would
always write a report, like, what you can
do in the context of this application with
this exercise.
Okay, that's nice.
I didn't...
Well, now in the bug bounty, I obviously have
to do it.
In pentesting, I admit I didn't.
And only, you know, in bug bounty, where you
have to convince the other side in every single
report that you have an actual impact, it
taught me to also start paying attention to
this during pentests.
Yeah.
Back when I worked there.
Yeah, I think that's...
Yeah, I mean...
Yeah, I think that's good.
Yeah.
We have also some, like, pentesting clients
who just accepted everything.
Whatever we write, they're okay with that.
But, yeah.
We had, of course, we had at Techuricum some,
you know, pre-written templates for, like,
many, many types of bugs.
But, I mean, I've used some of them.
But, I don't know.
There's something in me that I just don't
like to use template descriptions.
I want to make it, you know, more specific
to the application.
Of course, it also depended on the scale.
Because if I had, like, if there was, like,
an every possible bug in the application in
every possible place, it also happens, then
it probably doesn't make that much of a sense
to describe everything.
But, yeah.
Yeah, what I did, like, if I had, like, many
exercises in a single application, that's
also an interesting question.
Like, if you find the same vulnerability in
different places, would you report it as a
one bug with, like, different locations?
Or would you report it as a few bugs?
And, as usual, it depends.
Yeah.
Like, my approach was that, of course, when
I do path testing or bug bounty, it's usually
black box.
So, I cannot see the source code.
I don't know the exact root cause.
But, sometimes, you can see if you have a
few instances of probably the same bug.
And, when I assume that this is the case,
that, okay, this is, like, different locations,
different parameters, different endpoints.
But, the root cause is probably the same that
I reported it as a one bug.
But, if I thought that there are several different
root causes, then I would report this as distinct
bugs.
And, the main reason that's also really interesting,
I think, that in the path testing, we often
do retests.
So, yeah, we report bugs, the customer fixes
those bugs, and we need to do retests.
And, if I report, like, two different XSSs
in, you know, one bug, and then I do a retest,
and one is fixed, and one is not fixed, then
it's more difficult to state that in the report.
You need to say that it's partially fixed.
It's pretty bad.
I mean, you can do that, of course, but I
didn't like that.
So, if you have two separate issues, then
you can say, okay, this one is fixed, this
one is not fixed.
It's pretty obvious.
But, if you report many different things in
one bug, and they fix some of them, but, like,
not all of them, then it starts being not
that, you know, it's just not easy to grasp
what exactly it means, like, partially fixed.
You need to state exactly these endpoints
are fixed, these endpoints are not fixed,
and then it starts being, you basically kind
of start reporting this as a separate bug,
but in one bug.
You need to, you know, make your description
much longer.
So, yeah.
And, speaking of doing read tests, it also
taught me one very, I believe it's a very
important skill, is writing proof of concepts.
And, I have a nice story here.
It happened in the beginning of my career
as a pen tester, was that I did a pen test
of some application, and the client came back
with a read test, I think, a year later.
So, you don't remember about this application
anything, basically.
And then, I had, you know, proof of concept
or the description of the attack in the report,
and I wasn't able to replicate that.
It was too fake.
It was too bad to be able to, you know.
If you don't remember details, then you can't
do that from the description alone.
And, I spent a really long time trying to,
you know, remember what exactly I was doing,
how I was able to get to this place to mount
this attack.
And, yeah, that taught me that from, like,
that point, my proof of concepts are really
step by step.
You need to click here, you need to go here,
you need to make sure that you are logged
in as an account with this and that privileges
and stuff like that.
And, yeah, basically, my reason for writing
better proof of concept was that I should
be able to, you know, reproduce that back
from this proof of concept.
It should be, or maybe to put it another way,
if you have a person who never saw this application
before, then that person should be able to
reproduce the back based on your proof of
concept.
That was, like, my line of thinking.
Yeah, and that's good for bug bounty because
sometimes we think that we report the back
to someone that knows the application really
well.
But the truth is that often it's triaged by
a person who is responsible for many different
bug bounty programs, and they do not know
anything about the application you are reporting
the back currently.
So, I also, I don't know who told this where,
but I remember a tip from someone to actually
include things like creating an account, logging
in, using proper settings, setup or whatever
and only then doing the proof of concept.
And I also see, I'm not a triager, obviously,
but when I do the case studies, sometimes
I study a lot of, like, tens or hundreds of
bug bounty reports of a particular bug class.
And so, obviously, I want to, and I extract
some information about the report, and I see
that if there is a good proof of concept,
like step-by-step reproduction, is the quickest
way for me to, like, understand, okay, what
is this report about, what's the impact and
things like that.
And then I often don't even need to take a
look at the description and what they wrote
about the impact, because the good proof of
concept is a replacement of anything.
Yeah, that's right.
Also, yeah, also in Google, for instance,
like there are also some people on triage
when it comes to the VRP, Vulnerability Reward
Program.
And, you know, Google has like thousands of
applications, literally, and there are like,
I don't know, 50 people on triage.
So, there is no way that they know every single
application.
And also, I think, like, a good way of thinking
about it is that if you are a bug hunter and
you spend a lot of time on a single application,
then it's really, really likely that you know
more about this application than any person
from the triage.
Yeah.
So, keep, like, write as many details as you
possibly can.
You will make life easier for the people in
triage.
It will also make it easier to, you know,
grade your report and to understand what the
real impact is.
Yeah, especially when the bug is complex.
And speaking about the complexity, when I
look at your bugs from like 2013, 14, maybe
even 15, those exercises are often quite simple.
And then you started getting deeper into this
and reporting the more advanced exercises,
the mutation exercises, the crazy stuff a
lot of us don't even know about.
How did this transition happen and how did
you learn those more advanced things?
Yeah, that's an interesting question because
I don't think I have a good answer for that,
to be honest.
I think it just came.
I mean, one thing that truly happened was
that my approach in the beginning of my bug
hunting career was that I was trying to find
old applications.
Basically, I was using some Google hacking
and, yeah, Google hacking on Google and trying
to find, like, forgotten old application on
Google.
And it was possible.
There were, like, many, many of them.
And at some point, I was out of ideas.
Like, what else can I do?
At some point, you run out of ideas.
And, yeah, that was the point when I started
to just dig deeper into the application that
I know to find some bugs.
And also, another factor was I think it was
in 2015 or maybe 16 that Google introduced
research grants.
And the idea of research grants was that they
gave money upfront to bug hunters to specifically
look at certain applications.
So, of course, if you report a bug, you get
a normal reward, but the grant was supposed
to motivate you to look for some application.
And I think it really worked for me because
I looked at some applications, like, you know,
very, very carefully, digging very, very deep.
And I tried to understand exactly what happens,
yeah, what happens inside.
And I knew that I won't probably get some
easy XSS, like, you know, you could just get
parameter and you have an easy XSS.
So, I needed to understand what exactly happened
in the application, how it transforms, processes
the input, what are the sources, what are
the things.
So, yeah, but I don't have, like, a good answer
to, like, how exactly the transition happened.
I believe that it's just something that comes
with experience.
And, you know, when you report some simple
stuff, you also maybe at some point get kind
of bored of that and you want to do something
more interesting.
And, yeah, you start looking at, like, different
stuff.
Also, I think that for me, yeah, like, many
people, like, during the trainings that I
gave in my previous company, we will probably
talk about it a little bit later.
Yeah.
But many people ask me what is my methodology
for finding security bugs in Bug Bounty or
in PathOS.
And I didn't like the question because, you
know, some people have, like, some kind of
methodologies.
They like to do this and that and that.
Maybe they use some other references like
OS or whatnot.
But I'm the kind of person that uses my punch
and I don't have any specific methodology.
I'm just, you know, clicking randomly on the
application, seeing what it does.
I'm trying to understand what kind of library
it uses.
And, yeah, I just go with what my punch says.
And I know it's pretty bad from the, you know,
educational perspective because it doesn't
give any practical advice to anyone.
But, yeah, that's actually how I approach.
I just look at the application and I try to
see something specific in this application,
what can be a potential issue.
And, yeah, that actually works for me.
Yeah.
What tools do you use for this?
Is it mostly developer tools inside the browser?
Yeah.
When it comes to the client side issues, then
yes, I use DevTools in Chromium.
And let me think.
Yeah, I think that's pretty much it when it
comes to Chromium.
I sometimes write some scripts for myself
or some browser's extension.
What do they do?
Sorry?
What do those scripts do?
They usually do something automatically that
would be to deduce manually, like some kind
of transformation or like one of the things
that I actually made public was a script for
finding prototype pollution gadgets.
So it took a snippet of JavaScript and it
transformed it in such a way that if the script
is trying to access a non-existing property,
that it is a possible gadget for, you know,
client side prototype pollution.
Yeah.
Sometimes I'm just adding some logging because
I'm just interested in, you know, what happens
exactly in the application.
But in most cases, that was like pretty...
So basically just things to sort of speed
up the feedback loop of what happens.
Do you often debug the JavaScript inside the
browser or do you rather statically read it?
Yeah.
I'm a big proponent of dynamic analysis.
I think that's my main tool, how I work with
the code.
There are pretty nice tricks actually in the
Chromium DevTools.
I believe are not widely known.
Like, for instance, that there is a function
called debug that you can use in the DevTools
and you can pretty much debug everything.
You can even debug a setter on inner HTML
or something like that.
And I really, really like to use that, you
know, to find the piece of code that is interesting
for me quickly.
There are also features like, you know, practically
everybody who used debugger knows that you
can set a breakpoint in the DevTools.
But you can also set like a conditional breakpoint.
So the breakpoints that fired only in certain
conditions are met.
But also you can have, I think it's called
lockpoint.
So it is not a breakpoint, but you can, you
know, just do a constant lock in this line
whenever this kind of code is called.
So your code is not stopped because sometimes
it is pretty annoying, especially when the
application is doing like a lot of stuff.
For instance, if you try to set a breakpoint
on postMessage in any Google application,
then your debugger will stop like every single
second.
Just not usable at all.
Yeah.
So this kind of tricks is what I'm using.
I also, I don't remember why exactly I did
that, but I remember that at one point I also
used the Chromium, I mean, I used the Puppeteer,
it's called.
I think the Node.js library for controlling
Chromium.
Yeah.
Because, I don't know, the application was
doing something annoying and I wasn't able
to work with that.
And Puppeteer, I was just intercepting the
JavaScript and I was changing something in
the JavaScript.
So it's not that annoying.
Okay.
I don't remember the details, but I remember
I did something like that.
Okay.
This use case I didn't know about, but for
our listeners, in BBR review, I just finished
a four-part series about DevTools and all
the things that Michal described here are
there.
So you may want to check this out.
One thing I learned while writing those articles
and while writing the docs is that you can
reset frames while debugging.
So you can run over the same function over
and over again, which I didn't know about
and it also speeds up the work massively.
Yeah.
Another trick that I like to use is, for instance,
assume that you test an application that uses
some kind of HTML sanitizer and sometimes
it is pretty annoying to do that directly
from the application because, I don't know,
you need to pick some check boxes or you need
to press a button every single time and stuff
like that.
So I also like to find places that JavaScript
code does sanitization.
The assumption here is that it's client-side
sanitization.
And if you can get a reference function, like
in a debugger, because the nice thing about
using the debugger in Chromium or in any other
browser is that if you execute a command in
the console, then you are in the context of
where you are currently stopped.
So you can use the lock-on variables and stuff
like that.
So if I can find the method which performs
the sanitization, then I can just go to the
console and call it directly without doing
all this user interface stuff.
Yeah, that's a good tip.
How would you find this function?
Yeah, that's an interesting question.
There might be several ways to do that.
I might assume that if the application is
doing HTML sanitization, then it uses a browser
provided HTML parser, such as like the DOM
parser parsing string.
So I might try to set a breakpoint on that.
I might try to set a breakpoint on setter
of innerHTML.
If you know that the sanitized HTML is put
somewhere in the DOM tree, then in DevTools
it is also possible to set a breakpoint whenever
a DOM node changes.
So you can set a breakpoint on a certain DOM
node.
For instance, if add a child appended.
So then you can do that.
If you know that this is where the sanitized
HTML ends up.
And then you can go up through the stack trace
to find the place.
Because if you know that it is out here, then
somewhere near, hopefully, this generates.
So I focus on either the sink or the source.
So I'm trying to think.
Sometimes you can assume that there is a sanitizer.
You can just look for the word script.
Because if there is one tag that every single
sanitizer strips out, then it's script.
So you might be able to find it just by looking
for some strings that you assume that the
sanitizer will have.
Yeah, that's a good tip right here.
And what are your tips for reading?
Because I saw also some of your work was that
you found out new stuff in the browser or
new ways to define something in the browser.
How do you get knowledge about those changes
in the browser?
Basically from Twitter or X.
Okay.
I follow people who, I mean, among people
that I follow, there are also people that
work in browsers, like in Chromium, in the
Safari team, or in the Firefox team.
And when something new happens, then they
like to tweet about it.
There are also some Twitter accounts, like,
I don't remember the names, but something
like Intents2, I think it's called.
Because there is a process in all browsers
that if they want to introduce a new feature,
then they do something like Intents2 experiment,
Intents2 shape, stuff like that.
So there is some kind of documentation that
they want to introduce something new.
And then you can get the information about
that from the sources.
But sometimes these are just random tweets.
I remember that a few years ago, I did a security
analysis of Portal Elements.
And the inspiration from that was from a tweet
by Frederick Brown, which, by the way, is
in the Firefox team.
And that was a tweet, something along the
lines of, hey, you have a specification for
the Portal Element, but it doesn't have any
security consideration.
And I thought, ah, that's interesting, because,
I mean, the security considerations might
be empty, because this specification doesn't
really relate to security.
That might be the case.
But also, maybe nobody really thought about
the security consideration.
And, yeah, I believe the latter was the case
in Portal, unfortunately for me.
What happened later with the Portal Element?
I'm sorry?
What happened later with your research on
the Portal Element?
What happened after the question?
Because I think I saw your bug using the Portal
Element, the same margin policy bypass.
Yeah.
How did you get from reading the tweet into
finding the same margin policy bypass?
I see.
So, yeah, I read the spec, and I was just
trying to understand why do we even need portals?
What does it even do?
And it is similar to iframe.
That was the first thing that was easy to
notice.
But it's not exactly iframe.
The main difference was that in Portal Element,
you could call a method.
I think it was called activate.
And then the Portal Element is, like, upgraded
to be in the top frame, like, instantaneously,
without any load.
So, yeah, so, you know, the first thing that
I could notice was that, okay, it is similar
to iframe.
And in iframe, one thing that you can do is
that you can set the source attribute to,
like, JavaScript one.
So, yeah, I was trying to do the same thing
on Portal, and it worked.
But the question was, in what context does
the JavaScript execute?
And it turned out that in Portal, the JavaScript
executed in context of the page that was already
loaded.
It was pretty much equivalent to what happens
if you just, you know, paste the JavaScript
into the address bar.
So, if you enter the JavaScript and JavaScript
column and stuff, then it executes in the
currently loaded page.
And if you try to navigate Portal, then it
was pretty much equivalent to enter some stuff
in the address bar.
So, if you were on, like, accounts.google.com,
that was my example, and you could, you know,
enter JavaScript in the address bar.
If I tried to navigate Portal to JavaScript,
then it executed in the context of accounts.google.com.
But, you know, when I got the idea that this
is equivalent to entering a URL in the address
bar, then the natural next step for me was
that, okay, but in the address bar, you can
also navigate to a Pyle URL.
You cannot do that in iframe.
I mean, you cannot do that in iframe if you
are in the HTTPS protocol.
Because this is, like, it is not possible
to navigate to local resources from HTTPS.
But in Portal, when I tried to navigate to
Pyle, it worked.
It really showed the Pyle in the Portal.
So, what you could do was that you could navigate
to Pyle URL, like, etc password, and then
you can navigate to JavaScript to get the
content of that etc password.
So, that was not only same-origin policy bypass,
but it was also reading correct files, which
is even worse.
But, yeah, I think that this bug was, I think
it was kind of obvious.
I mean, in a way that it was the really natural
thing to check.
Okay, it is similar to iframe.
In iframe, this thing is blocked.
Let's see if it is blocked in a Portal.
I need one.
And that's pretty much the story about Portal.
I found, like, five or six bugs, I think.
And most of them were like, okay, this is
normally blocked.
The question is, is that blocked in Portal?
It's a bug report.
Do you know if the Portal element, because
back then it was in experimental mode or something
like this in Chromium?
I think it still is.
I don't think it's actually used.
I mean, they obviously fixed those bugs, but
yeah, I think it's also not under the enable
experimental web platform features, but it's
under a separate flag, like enable Portal.
Okay.
So even less people have that.
There's also an opposition from other browsers.
So I'm not really sure what is the status
of Portals.
I know that there were many, many, many security
issues because, like, I found the security
issues.
Some other people, when they found out that
something called Portal even exists, they
started to look for other issues.
And I know that there were several other,
like, memory corruption issues in Portals
as well.
So it was really a goldmine for bug hunters.
Does Google pay normally for features that
are experimental or they have, like, lower
bounty table for them?
I'm not exactly sure what the policy currently
is, to be honest.
I think the policy changed a few times in
the meantime, and I'm not sure if the bugs
would be rewarded today, to be honest.
Maybe they would, maybe they wouldn't.
I don't know what is the policy.
Okay.
And also, this is the bug in the browser,
not really in any website.
And it's also a shift that was present in
your career.
What was your drive to looking at bugs from
just bugs in normal websites to bugs in browsers?
Yeah, as I mentioned, when it comes to bug
hunting, I focused pretty much on the Google
web application.
And at some point, it started to be more and
more difficult to find bugs in, like, exercises
of the client-side issues and also the server-side
issues in Google applications that are not
like acquisitions, because acquisitions have
many bugs.
But the rewards for acquisitions are much
lower.
And yeah, I was interested in, you know, Google.com
domain-based.
And at some point, it started to be more and
more difficult.
And, you know, they, my feeling, my punch
was that there might be more bugs, but there
might be difficult to find using black box
approach.
And the nice thing about looking for bugs
in browsers is that all browsers are open
source.
I mean, all the engines are open source.
And if you believe that you are onto something,
and you can just look at the source code,
you can find what exactly happens.
It's not always easy to find, like, exactly
what part of the source code is responsible
for the functions you are currently testing.
But, you know, the easiest way is that if
you have any error message, then it's usually
the easiest way to find by the message placed
in the code.
But, yeah, I think that the portal element
was actually the first thing that I did that
was related directly to the browser.
And I believe that it actually motivated me
to look more.
So one thing was that it was more and more
difficult to find bugs in web applications.
The other thing was that, you know, you have
source code of the browsers, but also it just
didn't know before that when I tried to find
some bugs in a browser mechanism, then I was
able to do that.
That was a really interesting lesson for me.
By the way, I think that generally my lesson,
like during my whole life, is that you might
have some assumptions, whether you are good
at something, but the assumption might be
wrong.
I mean, you might think that you like doing
something, but when you do that, more than
you started to see that, okay, it's not actually
what you like.
And the other way around, you might not.
Because I think that before portals, I didn't
even think about testing browsers.
But, okay, I tried that and it went well.
In the beginning of my pentesting career,
I thought that the most interesting area of
pentesting is the infrastructure.
I remember that I saw some presentations about
Metasploit and stuff like that, and I thought
it's super, super interesting, and I want
to do infrastructure pentesting.
And I did, a little bit.
But it just happened that I was better at
doing web, basically.
So, you know, at some point I decided that
I don't think that I want to do the infrastructure
anymore, at least not much of it, and I want
to focus more and more on web, because it
just happens that I'm better at it.
And I think that's a nice place to share also
a fun story, how my interest in security in
general started, because it was an infrastructure
thing.
I think I was in high school at that point.
I already knew a little bit of programming.
I programmed in Python and Visual Basic.
That was actually my first programming language.
And I knew some stuff around, but networking
was like pure magic for me.
I didn't know at all how networking works.
And one day, like randomly, I found an article
on Wikipedia about ARP spoofing.
And, you know, I always assume that what happens
in the network is like some magical, super
advanced algorithm.
But then you read how the ARP protocol works,
and it's like super, super simple, super naive.
And then you see how the attack works.
And the attack is like super easy in theory.
Basically, for those of you who don't know,
the basic idea of the ARP spoofing attack
is that imagine that you are standing in front
of a group of people, and you are asking,
who is John?
And you assume that the John will arise.
But somebody else might rise their hand.
And then you give something that was supposed
to go to John to that person.
And this is pretty much how it works in networking.
We trust that when we ask, who is this IT
address or this MAC address, then we trust
that the right machine responds.
And then I learned about a tool.
I don't remember how it's called.
Anyway, it doesn't matter.
But there was a tool with which you could
mount the ARP spoofing.
And I tried that in my local network.
And, you know, it was in a year before like
HTTPS everywhere.
So it was pretty nice that I could tell my
brother, hey, go to this website, and suddenly
some other text showed up.
And that was pretty much my first proof of
concept that I did of an attack.
That, you know, some random text changed on
some pages because everything was under HTTP.
And, yeah, at that point, that was really
a turning point for me.
Because, hey, the network is not pure magic.
It's actually pretty simple.
At least some of the protocols are simple.
Not all of them, of course.
But, yeah, so it all started with infrastructure
things.
And now I'm not doing any infrastructure at
all.
To be honest, when I started learning about
security, I also wasn't attracted to web security
at all.
I don't really know why, but I thought I want
to do like reverse engineering or something
in this direction.
And I think I was just afraid of complexity
of the web.
And then I just started learning it for some
reason.
And I got into it.
And apparently it works well.
There's also a good book called, I think,
Be So Good They Can't Ignore You.
And it really touches upon the fact that to
like something, you just have to become good
enough at something.
And then you sort of start liking it.
And it's against people that are saying that
you have some natural abilities for one profession
only.
And I think the book is really good.
I can recommend it to anyone.
But the takeaway is just when you are getting
good at something, then you sort of start
liking it naturally.
Obviously, that's not always the case.
I do think that people have some predispositions.
Are they more analytical or more relationship
oriented or whatever?
But within such a space as security where
it's pretty much similar skill set, I think
for most people, they could like a lot of
different branches of security.
And they could jump around and learn pretty
much anything.
The nice thing is also that if you know one
area of security well, then it's easier to
jump into another one because you have some
background and you understand what it's all
about a little bit better.
I mean, if I was supposed to do, I don't know,
a Linux exploit development, then I would
start pretty much from zero.
But I think given some of the background that
I have, it would be easier for me to jump
into that topic than to a person who didn't
have any experience with security at all.
Yeah, 100%.
So yeah, that's also nice that all of this
experience that you have can also be useful.
Or maybe if you have a different kind of background
than other people working in this field, that
could also be useful because this background
might come useful in certain situations.
You mentioned reverse engineering.
So if you are a reverse engineer with good
knowledge about web, it can come useful if
you happen to reverse engineer something related
to web in some way that the other people might
not be very familiar with.
And speaking of learning, I have never found
a prototype pollution bug.
And what would be your tips for me to find
one?
Yeah, that's an interesting question.
Because in Bug Bounty, I also didn't report
a single prototype pollution bug.
So that's also a little bit of a shift.
At some point, I started sharing more research
stuff instead of just bugs.
And I just found prototype pollution interesting.
I mean, okay, we might say that I reported
some bugs, but it wasn't in Bug Bounty.
It was like, I don't know, I think I reported
that to Don't Purify.
How about the Jibana RCE?
Yeah, that's also an interesting story.
That's a bug that wasn't found by me.
It was just found by somebody else.
I don't know even by who, to be honest.
The story here was that there was a training
organized by Securiton.
There was one participant that said that he
wants to understand prototype pollution better.
And he found this Jibana vulnerability that
doesn't have a public proof of concept.
And he was able to find what kind of module
has this vulnerability.
And yeah, we can look at that and maybe we
can find some kind of scenario.
So yeah, that's also something that's happened
a lot in my career.
That some things happen by accident, pretty
much.
Because if it wasn't for that one participant
of the training, then maybe I would have dived
into prototype pollution a little bit later.
But yeah, that was the motivation.
But anyway, prototype pollution was more of
a research project for me.
I just found it interesting.
I believe that this is not a bug that is much
talked about.
And it was just interesting for me from purely
technical perspective.
And yeah, I was just trying to understand
how viable this attack scenario is.
And of course, I did try to test some Google
properties for prototype pollution.
But I wasn't able to find any bugs.
Yeah, but when it comes to tips, I think there
is a really good research.
I think it was called just something like
exploiting client-side prototype pollution.
Something like that.
And they shared some techniques, how they
found the sources for prototype pollution.
Like if you are looking for client-side prototype
pollution, then you can just randomly add
a proto parameters to get the bones to JSON
everywhere.
And you can just look into your browser dev
tools to see if you can see your properties
on object prototype.
I think that the way Chromium sorts the properties,
it's like a side effect of an implementation,
is that the new properties are always in the
beginning.
So if you look like an object prototype, then
your new properties should be at the beginning.
I'm not 100% sure that it happens, but I think
that was the case.
I also think that the BURP suite has some
features, some new features related to prototype
pollution, but I didn't have much chance to
test that.
There is the DOM invader, which is like a
browser extension actually.
And I absolutely love this extension for DOM
access.
And it also has some features to find prototype
pollution, but the prototype pollution features
I haven't tested actually.
Now I think I probably should turn it on and
see what comes.
Yeah, that might be interesting to see what
kind of issues you can find.
Yeah.
And speaking of trainings, what kinds of trainings
did you lead and for who?
Yeah.
So during my last two years at Securitium,
I was really focused on giving trainings,
public talks, basically on education.
And so I had many different trainings.
The most popular one was called Web of Infinite
Security.
And it was a two-day workshop about SQL injection,
XSS, authorization issues, authentication
issues, server-side request forgery, and stuff
like that.
And we just taught people about security issues
they can expect in web applications by showing
them how they can be exploited.
The participants got a training license for
the web, so they could work with that themselves.
And yeah, the basic idea, the usual target
for these trainings were developers to try
to teach them about web security and what
kind of security issues they can expect.
And yeah, I remember that in the beginning,
I kind of expected that when people leave
the training, then they should just write
super secure code after that, because they
learned everything that they need to know
about at least the basic security stuff.
But at some point, I understood that this
is not what happens.
And I considered a success of my training
if a person can recognize a security issue.
Like when they write a code, then they can,
you know, have suddenly a light bulb above
their head that, hey, I think there might
be something wrong with this code.
So my goal was to build some kind of intuition,
because if we talk about some specific security
issues, then we can also try to generalize
them a little bit.
And yeah, I would consider a success if a
person, when writing a code, thinks twice,
hey, this probably is something that might
be not safe.
But also something that happened a few times
during the training was that after the first
day of the training, people started to test
their own applications.
And on the second day, we started the training,
and they said, hey, we found this bug in our
application.
That was actually super cool, and it's one
of the best things that could happen on the
training, because immediately you know that
for the people, it was ready to go to the
training.
Yeah.
What did you see them getting wrong the most
often about security?
I think the understanding of attack scenarios,
the stuff that we talked about before.
Because one, an example, one of the arguments
that was brought a few times was that when
I say that we have client-side HTML sanitizers,
and that you probably want to use client-side
HTML sanitizers, because you use exactly the
same HTML parser that is used by your browser,
so it makes sense.
And then some people would argue that, okay,
but if it's client-side sanitizer, then you
can disable it or stuff like that.
If it happens on the client, how we can trust
it?
And yeah, that was the part when you needed
to describe what is the threat model.
And I believe that it is widely, it is really
widely, widely misunderstood.
I mean, it's not easy if you don't really
also, if you don't think about it that much,
and it's really easy to misunderstand.
But I also had a training that was called
front-end security training, and it was about
XSS.
Basically, the whole first day was about XSS,
and the second day was about other front-end
issues.
And yeah, the thing that I was trying to,
I was hoping for the people to understand
was that the attack scenario here, basically
for most front-end issues, is that you send
a link to someone, and then you can do something.
Because if we start talking that you can do
something in the dev tools of the browsers,
or that you can, I don't know, intercept the
HTTPS traffic, in theory you can do that.
If you have some impossible supercomputer
or you find a bug in the algorithm, you can
do that.
But this is not something that we care about
in context of issues like XSS.
It's just completely outside of the threat
model.
And it is very tricky how to describe that
to people so that they understand.
Even HTTPS, which is the most widely deployed
security mechanism in the world, there were
people who asked, if the site had HTTPS, why
did they have a security breach?
And we might laugh about it a little bit,
but it's actually a really tricky educational
issue.
How can we make people understand what they
are protecting against when they use HTTPS
or any other security mechanism?
Another good example, I believe, is that if
you have an encrypted messenger on your WhatsApp
or Signal or whatever, end-to-end encryption,
nobody can read the messages.
But if you leave your phone unlocked on the
table, it doesn't matter if the communication
is encrypted end-to-end because anyone who
can just take the phone can read the messages.
And sometimes in the internet you can see
some comments or discussions, hey, they use
Signal, it has end-to-end encryption.
How the government organization was able to
decrypt the message?
And they probably didn't even have to decrypt
anything.
They probably had direct access to the screen.
So it's really, really tricky because we have
many, many different mechanisms that prevent
some specific attacks.
And people who, I mean, I believe that people
should have some general understanding about
security.
By the way, I really think that it is something
that should be taught in school, you know,
in the informatics lessons, like some basics.
I mean, I don't know what is currently being
taught at school, maybe it is, actually.
So people should have some general understanding,
but I can understand that they do need to
know that HTTPS also keeps the integrity of
the data because when you talk about HTTPS
you usually think that it encrypts, but it's
not all it does, actually.
And it probably doesn't matter for most people
to also check the integrity of the data, but
it is actually, from the cryptographic perspective,
super, super important.
If it wouldn't do that, then it would be a
really bad protocol, to be honest.
So, yeah, that was tricky because if you get
a question about, you know, security, about
the threat model, about the attack scenario,
it's very tricky to answer that question,
to describe it, without some browser context.
And, yeah, of course there are, like, other
things that people get wrong, like I don't
know how to use BERT.
I mean, I love BERT, but let's be honest,
user interface is not the best in the world,
especially when you need to use it for the
first time.
But that's something that you can just learn,
but the attack scenario, the threat modeling,
is something that you need to understand to
kind of get that, what's it all about.
So, yeah, I think it mainly came up in the
front-end training that, you know, stuff like,
does it make sense to have some kind of security
mechanism in the browser?
Because, like, you can bypass everything that
happens in the browser.
That was the argument.
Yeah, you can.
I mean, the argument that I typically use
is that just because you can do something
on your own computer, it doesn't mean that
it's easy to do on somebody else's computer.
So you can run DevTools in your own browser
and you can delete everything, you can change
the code as much as you like, but it doesn't
mean that it's easy to do to someone else.
And I think that's the shortest answer to
this question, but, yeah, it's really interesting
to, you know, dig deeper.
And it's also very relevant, you know, to
path testing and to back-binding reports to
also understand the threat models and if something
is a vulnerability or how severe of a vulnerability
that is.
Yeah, I think also from my experience, I don't
do trainings now, but I used to, and I think
server-side vulnerabilities are so much easier
to explain to people than client-side stuff.
Because with XSS, you have the same modern
policy, you have different types of XSSs.
Like, for example, when you have an XSS in
the uploaded file, it's really hard to explain
to the person that if it is a sandbox domain,
it's not a risk, but if it's a normal domain,
it is a risk, even though there is nothing
on the page, but you can do the request.
There's so much complexity there that I really
think XSS, even though it's the most popular
vulnerability type, I think, from the web
vulnerabilities, it is super complex and super
misunderstood.
Yeah, that's right.
I also think that the typical proof-of-concept
for XSS also doesn't do it any favors because
people always see the alert one, they don't
have any idea what you can realistically do.
That's basically what I started with my trainings.
Before even saying what XSS exactly is, how
we can exploit that, I was just showing a
real example that you can get some data.
Like, I had a demonstration that you could
take over an admin account in WordPress thanks
to XSS.
I started with that and I was just saying
that from now on, you will see mostly the
alert one, but keep in mind that instead of
the alert one, we could do all the stuff that
I just showed.
Yeah.
I think it was all new for many people, so
on the second day, some of the people kind
of forgot about that and asked again, like,
okay, but yeah, I have that, but I can't do
alert one, so what?
Yeah, but I also learned over...
I mean, I remember that when I started doing
trainings, I think it was in 2014 or 15, I
assumed that people will know more about security
in general, and I thought that the most stuff
that are widely known, that there actually
are, and like, for instance, something that
kind of surprised me, but it doesn't surprise
me anymore, is JSPack, which is a way to write
JavaScript code.
It is really widely known among security people
because it's very useful if you want to bypass
some filter, then you can perhaps use it,
but for developers, I mean, if they are interested
in some low-level details of how JavaScript
works, then they know about JSPack, but many
people didn't even hear about it.
It was kind of surprising for me in the beginning
because it's like super interesting stuff
about JavaScript, but the thing is that they
don't need to know that at all because why?
They don't need to use these tricks, like,
they don't need to know that you can use,
I don't know, array constructed constructor
to have access to a function that works like
an even.
It's super useful for security people, but
developers need that.
Yeah, I've had a similar realization one day
when I think we were talking with the Java
developer while developing Java deserialization
exploits or gadgets or whatever, or asking
them about some reflections or whatever, and
they just didn't even know how to execute
system-level code in Java because it is actually
a good thing because they don't do it in normal
web applications, and we know a few ways in
every single language how to execute code.
Yeah, so that was a really good insight that
the developers need other stuff than security
people and something that might seem obvious
for us, even really obvious or even irrelevant
for them.
On the training, I also had some challenges
related to SQL injection, and you needed to
bypass some filter, encode the data, escape
it somehow, and yeah, people didn't know many
of the stuff because, let's be honest, if
you need to write a SQL query, then you are
a developer, and you would try to write it
as legible as possible, and when we are trying
to bypass some filters, then we are doing
pretty much the opposite.
We are trying to use as many obscure facts
about how SQL is sparse as we possibly can,
so yeah, at some point I understood that,
okay, I know that you probably, I mean I had
some kind of cheat sheet from some point that
here are some useful features of SQL, JavaScript,
whatever that you might need in the challenges,
but yeah, I remember that.
In the very beginning, I was so surprised.
How can people not know that?
Yeah, okay, Michał, last question.
I saw you started a YouTube channel yourself
recently.
What are your plans regarding this?
Yeah, so my plan, I don't have any specific
plans about what I want to do with the channel.
Probably I will have some videos.
I mean my first video was not technical, I
think not that technical, and it was pretty
well received, which I think is pretty nice,
and I'll have some other ideas or other topics
to talk about that are not purely technical,
but I think people might find them interesting.
Like one of the topics is like the attack
scenarios and the threat model and like to
understand what we can do with some kind of
attack.
I specifically want to talk about HTML sanitization
on the client and why it makes sense, because
recently I saw a YouTube short, I don't remember
what was the channel, but it was about the
sanitizer API that is introduced in browsers,
and there were like many comments under that
video about the sanitization must be done
on the server because you have it on the client,
then it's bad, you can bypass it, you can
remove it, disable it, and yeah, that was
an inspiration for me.
Okay, I think that's something that we have
to explain to people so that they understand
that it actually makes sense to sanitize on
the client, and that's a good excuse to have
a little bit of a browser talk about threat
modeling, I think, in general.
Yeah, we'll link this video in the description.
I posted really nice stories about bugs from
Michal's bug bounty journey.
For now, Michal, thank you so much for joining
me today.
Loads of knowledge for me and for my audience.
Where can people find you to follow you on
the internet?
I think the best place is on Twitter or X.
My handle is SecurityMB, and from that you
can see links from all other places where
I'm currently at, but basically I'm using
mainly Twitter.
Okay, once again, thank you so much for joining
me today.
Thank you for the invitation and for the nice
talk we had.
What a great episode!
If you want to watch the video on Michal's
channel about his bug bounty reports, check
out the link that's in the description.
And if you want to listen to another interview,
I suggest you this one with Johann Carson,
who went from nothing to six-digit bug bounty
earnings in only one year.
For now, thank you for listening and goodbye.